Finding Aid for the Giorgio Nicodemi Papers LSC.0009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Giorgio Nicodemi papers
1884-1952
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nicodemi, Giorgio, 1891-1967
LSC.0009
11.2 linear feet (28 boxes)
This archive consists of Professor Giorgio Nicodemi's working files of readings (preprints, printed lectures, honorary essays, etc.); photographs of artists' works (most annotated by Nicodemi); clippings; notes; small books and more ephemeral publications; and a few letters and other correspondence, often tipped into relevant publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nicodemi Estate, circa 1968.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9925311743606533
Biographical / Historical
Giorgio Nicodemi was an Italian museologist, essayist and art historian. He was born in Trieste on May, 29 1891 and dided in Milan on June 9, 1967. In 1919, he became a director of the Civici Musei of Brescia and of the Biblioteca Queriniana, where Nicodemi remained until 1928. In 1928, he became a director of the Civici Musei of Milan, including museums of the Castello Sforzesco. From 1928 until 1938, Nicodemi also taught art history at the Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore.
Scope amd Content
This archive consists of Professor Giorgio Nicodemi's working files of readings (preprints, printed lectures, honorary essays, etc.); photographs of artists' works (most annotated by Nicodemi); clippings; notes; small books and more ephemeral publications; and a few letters and other correspondence, often tipped into relevant publications.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials retain their existing order. The character of these materials (often annotated by Nicodemi) tells us that Nicodemi must have filed them in alphabetical order by author/scholar and, in the case of the photographs, by artist.
Separated Materials
At an unknown date, Getty Photo Archivists were invited to take those Nicodemi photographs appropriate for their collection.
Nicodemi, Giorgio, 1891-1967 -- Archives
- Miscellanea: preprints of articles, undated (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
  Scope and Contents
  This includes preprints of articles were for the most part published in the first quarter of this century in the field of Italian Renaissance art history (several in other areas of study).
- Miscellanea: preprints, single issues of scholarly and popular journals, assorted plates and prints, bound issues of BOLLETTINO DEL COMUNE DI NAPOLI, 1916 (Box 6)
- Miscellanea: preprints, printed lectures, honorary publications, copies of journals, 1925 November 29, Summer 1959 (Box 7)
  Includes an unbound copy of Corso Elementare Di Ornamenti Architettonici Del Professore Domenico Moglia, PartePrima (Milano 1842), Frederick Hartt review of Leonardo's Trattato (McMahon and Steinitz titles) from College Art Journal xviii, 4 Summer 1959, Igino Benvenuto Supino's Leon Battista Alberti E Il Tempio Malatestiano: Memoria presentata alla R. Accademia delle Scienze dell Instituto di Bologna Classe di Scienze Morali nella Sessions del 29 novembre 1925.
- Miscellanea: preprints and "Opuscoletti" on various topics, 1838-1944 (Box 8)
  This includes Giuseppe Martinola's honorary essay on L'Architetto Luigi Fontana Di Muggio (1812-1877) printed in 1944, with tipped in personal letter from author to Nicodemi; and Nicodemi's own writings.
- Miscellanea: preprints, 1884-1920s (Box 9)
- Miscellanea: catalogues in honor of various artists (often posthumous), notes and gallery proofs, clippings, 1959 (Box 10)
  This includes catalogues in honor of Eugenio Spreafico, Enrico Ludolf Verworner, Arturo Tosi, Teofilo Patini, Giovanni Omiccioli, Sirio Terracuio Magni, Sante Monachesi; notes and gallery proofs on Edouard Vuillard exhibit catalogue (Milano, Palazzo Reale, 1959).
- Miscellanea: handwritten notes, clippings, photographs, correspondence regarding celebrations honoring Leonardo da Vinci on the fifth centenary of his birth, 1952 (Box 11)
- Miscellanea: photographs A-D, undated (Box 12)
  This includes preprint with color plates re: medieval costume.
- Miscellanea: handwritten notes, typed notes, preprints, photographs, undated (Box 13)
- Miscellanea: photographs, single journal issues, portraits, undated (Box 14)
- Miscellanea: photographs, notes, letters, undated (Box 15)
- Miscellanea: photographs, undated (Box 16)
- Miscellanea: photographs, related printed newsletters and typescripts, undated (Box 17)
- Miscellanea: photographs and illustrations, related preprints and extracts, correspondence, notes, typescripts, undated (Box 18)
- Miscellanea: photographs and illustrations, notes, book signatures, news clippings, exhibition catalogues, typescripts, preprints, undated (Box 19)
- Photographs of artists' works, undated (Box 20)
- Photographs of artists' works, exhibition catalogue, undated (Box 21)
- Miscellanea: photographs of artists' works, selected journal issues, preprints, notes, undated (Box 22)
- Miscellanea: photographs and illustrations, notes, clippings, undated (Box 23)
- Miscellanea: photographs, illustrations, clippings, pamphlets, notes, preprints, undated (Box 24)
- Miscellanea: photographs, typescripts, notes, catalogues, undated (Box 25)
- Photographs, illustrations, notes, undated (Box 26)
- Miscellanea: photographs, correspondence, clippings, notes, undated (Box 27)
- Photographs of artists' works, undated (Box 28)